Duane Family Collection 1764-1933 Mss.SMs.Coll.2
American Philosophical Society
Duane Family Collection
1764-1933
Mss.SMs.Coll.2
American Philosophical Society
2.0 Linear feet
A leading national opinion maker and influential regional politician, tied by marriage to the families of Benjamin Franklin and cognate families, William Duane (1760-1835) played key roles in the field of political journalism, as well as national, Pennsylvania and local Philadelphia politics. Editor of the Aurora, William Duane (1760-1835) assured himself gratitude from Jefferson and the Republicans and enmity from President Adams and the Federalists for his open and effective attacks on Federalist policies. His son William John Duane (1780-1865), was a prominent member of the Pennsylvania legislature, a legal advisor to Stephen Girard, Solicitor for many of Philadelphia's premier institutions, and Secretary of the Treasury of the United States (June-September 1833). The Duane Family Collection contains a diverse assemblage of personal and professional correspondence relating to family members, with interesting material relating to William Duane (1760-1835), his son, William John Duane (1780-1865), grandson William Duane (1808-1882), great-grandson Charles Williams Duane (1837-1915), and other relations. The collection includes unique correspondence from and relating to Benjamin Franklin's family, as well as correspondence with Thomas Jefferson and other leading figures from the early nineteenth century. The collection also includes prints, photographs of family members, as well as some maps.
2 lin. ft.
Duane family
Biographical/Historical note
A leading national opinion maker and influential regional politician, tied by marriage to the families of Benjamin Franklin and cognate families, William Duane (1760-1835) played key roles in the field of political journalism, as well as national, Pennsylvania and local Philadelphia politics. Editor of the Aurora, William Duane (1760-1835) assured himself gratitude from Jefferson and the Republicans and enmity from President Adams and the Federalists for his open and effective attacks on Federalist policies. His son William John Duane (1780-1865), was a prominent member of the Pennsylvania legislature, a legal advisor to Stephen Girard, Solicitor for many of Philadelphia's premier institutions, and Treasurer of the United States (June-September 1833).
Born near Lake Champlain, NY in 1760 to John and Anastasia Duane, William Duane was sent to Ireland at the age of eleven to be raised by his mother's family. Receiving a quality education due to his mother's relative wealth, he was nonetheless disinherited upon his marriage to a Protestant. Moving to England for a short time to stay with an uncle and learn the printing business, he then removed to India in 1784 in order establish himself. Starting up a newspaper, The World, in Calcutta, William became quite successful in acquiring increased business and real estate holdings. Falling upon disfavor with the East India Company, he was subsequently kidnapped and involuntarily shipped back to England. Failing redress in compensation from the East India Company or Parliament, he decided to become a reporter on Parliament for a journal which ultimately became the London Times. Returning to America in 1795, William began work for the Aurora, a paper established by Benjamin Franklin Bache. William took over the editorship in of the Aurora in 1798 upon Bache's death, and transformed the Aurora from a local Republican paper into a state and national political organ. A partisan publication, the Aurora under William Duane became even more heavily associated with Jeffersonian politics and a thorn in the Federalists side. William became the focus of President Adams ire, with his ridicule of the Alien and Sedition Acts generating a great deal of hostile attention. Often openly physically attacked by Federalist sympathizers, he persevered and was credited by Jefferson with securing Pennsylvania and therefore the Presidency for him. William became heavily influential in Pennsylvania state politics, with the ability to determine the nomination of at least two Pennsylvania governors. With the War of 1812, William was appointed U. S. Adjutant General with the rank of Colonel. In 1822, he sold the Aurora and entered a new phase in his life. William traveled throughout South America in 1822, developing contacts, and surveying the political situation. Upon his return, he was appointed prothonotary of the Supreme Court of Pennsylvania for the eastern district, a post he retained until his death in 1835.
A politician of some regional prominence and briefly a member of Andrew Jackson's cabinet, William John Duane (1780-1865) was an influential figure in both national and Pennsylvania politics. Beginning his career working for his father William Duane (1760-1835) at the Aurora, William John Duane then managed a bookstore and printing business in the nation's new capital, Washington, D. C., responsible (along with his father) for printing the Congressional Journal (Senate) 1803-1808. Following his marriage in 1805, he entered the paper business, managing sales. In 1809, he was elected to the Pennsylvania state legislature, a relationship he never entirely removed himself from - even when not in office. With an inheritance from his father-in-law in 1811, he studied law and entered the bar in 1815. William John served as solicitor for many of Philadelphia's institutions, including the Carpenters' Company, as well as legal advisor to Stephan Girard. He wrote tracts which were greatly influential to Andrew Jackson's winning of Pennsylvania's vote in the Presidential election of 1828. Offered the mayoralty of Philadelphia, he declined. He was subsequently appointed by Andrew Jackson as one of three commissioners under the treaty with Denmark. William John Duane rejected an appointment by Jackson as U. S. District Attorney, and again rejected an appointment as Director of the Bank of the United States. In 1832 he did agree to accept the appointment as Secretary of the Treasury under Jackson, and assumed the office in June of 1833. Disagreeing with Jackson on the fundamental issue of removing Federal monies from the Bank of the United States (an early pre-cursor to the Federal Reserve), William John Duane spent the next few months attempting to negotiate with Jackson, finally refusing to cooperate, which resulted in his termination as Secretary of the Treasury on September 23, 1833. Upon his return to Philadelphia, William John Duane fell back on a limited private practice of law, supplemented by monies he had previously set aside. He became one of the Directors of Girard College for a term of office, and subsequently retired from public life.
Scope and Contents note
The Duane Family Collection contains personal papers, correspondence, notes, printed materials, prints, photographs, and glass slides that have derived from and are related to generations of the Duane family. At the core of the collection, is a selection of personal and professional correspondence relating to William Duane (1760-1835), his son, William John Duane (1780-1865), grandson William Duane (1808-1882), and great-grandson Charles Williams Duane (1837-1915).
The materials relating to the Duane family include William Duane's (1760-1835) correspondence with Colonial British officials, as well as personages such as Thomas Jefferson, and prominent men in the Pennsylvania legislature. Of general note is correspondence relating to Revolutionary French officials taking over Caribbean islands, correspondence relating to Benjamin Franklin, an 1806 letter from Andrew Jackson, and later correspondence (William John Duane 1780-1865) to and from President Andrew Jackson.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Acquired 1957-1980; gift of Morris Duane.
Related Archival Materials note
The American Philosophical Society Library's catalog lists 23 items related to the Duane Family, or individual family members. Included in our manuscript collections is the Castle Bach Collection, and a large number of collections relating to Benjamin Franklin.
Other related major manuscript collections are held at the John Stevens Collection, National Museum of American History; and the Peter Force Library, Library of Congress.
The APS has a partial run of the newspaper, the Aurora.
Bibliography
A collection of all the laws of the province of Pennsylvania (Philadelphia: Benjamin Franklin, 1742).
Duane, Morris, Duane, Morris & Heckscher (Philadelphia: Printed for the firm only, 1979). 340.0973 D85d
Merrill, John Houston, Memoranda relating to the Mifflin family (Philadelphia: privately printed, 1890).
William Duane Pamphlet Collection (25 entries).
Early American History Note
The Duane Family Collection is a rich and diverse collection that includes papers from numerous prominent citizens from the colonial era to the antebellum period. The bulk of the collection is from 1800-1840. These letters often touch on political affairs as they relate to Duane’s editorship of the Aurora. Also of particular note, the collection contains a series of letters on early national politics with some significant presidential correspondence. There are also family letters between William John Duane’s son, also named William Duane, and his sisters Mary and Sarah Duane that discusses social events, courtship, and gossip about individuals, including details on the deaths of two of Duane’s friends in a duel. Some of the early documents (before 1800) include records of Duane’s newspaper business in India, where he operated in the 1790s as a dissenting voice against the East India Company’s policies.
Perhaps because of William Duane’s connection to the Aurora, there are a series of Franklin family letters from the colonial and revolutionary eras. Also because of Duane’s prominence as a newspaperman, there is a range of other letters, including some from very prominent figures (Andrew Jackson, Stephen Girard, Thomas Jefferson, John Quincy Adams, Henry Clay) in the early republic. Many of the letters that Duane received touch upon important issues of the day. Indeed, some appear to be written as dispatches meant to appear in Duane’s newspaper. Topics of letters Duane received include reports on India, the French Revolution, trade, Jefferson’s election, diplomacy, and other world affairs. The letters to the editor that survive in this collection also offer insight into the workings of the early national press and reporting.
Of particular note, the collection contains a series of Andrew Jackson letters ranging from 1806 to 1833 (bulk 1830s) that often discuss politics. The 1806 letter discusses Jackson’s financial straits because he lost four slave ships, which put him in arrears. Letters from 1833 to William John Duane, a Jackson-appointed Director of the Bank of the United States and Secretary of the Treasury, describe Jackson’s plans for dismantling the Bank and establishing a “new system.” Duane rejected Jackson’s plans and the correspondence chronicles the tensions between the two men that developed following Duane’s refusal to follow Jackson’s plans. Duane’s defiance ultimately led to his resignation and replacement by Roger Taney.
Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848; Bache family; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867; Bache, Catherine Wistar, 1770-1820; Bache, Richard, 1737-1811; Bache, Sarah Franklin, 1743-1808; Bartram, George Washington, 1784-1853; Biddle, Nicholas, 1786-1844; Clay, Henry, 1777-1852; Dallas, George Mifflin, 1792-1864; Duane, James, 1733-1797; Duane, William John, 1780-1865; Duane, William, 1760-1835; Duane, William, 1808-1882; Franklin family; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790; Franklin, Deborah Read Rogers, 1708-1774; Frémont, John Charles, 1813-1890; Girard, Stephen, 1750-1831; Hopkinson, Joseph, 1770-1842; Ingersoll, Charles Jared, 1782-1862; Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Kendall, Amos, 1789-1869; Leib, Michael, 1761-1822; Madison, James, 1751-1836; McKean, Thomas, 1734-1817; McLane, Allen, 1786-1845; Moore, George Washington, 1814-1899; Rittenhouse, David, 1732-1796; Sergeant, John, 1779-1852; Snyder, Simon, 1759-1819; Taney, Roger Brooke, 1777-1864; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841; Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852; Woodbury, Levi, 1789-1851; Aurora (Philadelphia, Pa.); Beyond Early America; Business and Skilled Trades; Business Records and Accounts; Early National Politics; Family Correspondence; General Correspondence; Government Affairs; Ireland - Politics and government - 19th century; Jackson, Andrew--1767-1845--Correspondence.; Newspapers--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia; Philadelphia (Pa.)--Politics and government--1783-1815; Philadelphia (Pa.)--Politics and government--19th century.; Philadelphia (Pa.)--Social life and customs; Political Correspondence; Presidents--United States--Correspondence.; Printing and Publishing; Social Life and Custom; United States - History - 1815-1861; United States--Politics and government--1783-1815; United States--Politics and government--1816-1861; United States--President (1829-1837: Jackson)
- Series I. Correspondence, 1764-1933; 1.5 lin. feet
  - Autograph, 1764; 1 pg.; Duane, Matthew, 1707-1785
    Scope and Contents note
    Remnant of letter from Mathew Duane, uncle to William Duane.
    General note
    From scrapbook.
  - ALS to Benjamin Franklin, [1764]; 4 pgs.; Franklin, Deborah Read Rogers, 1708-1774
    Contains news from home, including a list of items desired from England. Mentions daughter Sally, son William, Mr. Henderson, Mr. Galloway, and Mrs. Stephenson.
    Old call number B:D852.3.
  - Declaration of trust of lands, 1770 May 1; 1 pg.; Duane, James, 1733-1797
    Old call number B:D852.
  - ALS to Deborah Franklin, 1771 December 3; 3 pgs.; Bache, Richard, 1737-1811
    Has met with father (B. Franklin) who received him with "open arms." Mentions hospitality of Mrs. Stevenson and Mrs. Hewson.
  - ALS to Steven Cleveland, 1776 July 30; 4 pgs.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Instructions to Capt. Cleveland, directing him to sail to France to deliver a sensitive "cargo" to a Mr. Merk? in Bordeaux and receive a new "cargoe" from a Sammuel Delap? Is instucted to contact Silas Deane--political and financial agent in France.
    Old call number B:D852. 1957 1344ms. Reference legal file for further explanatory notes.
  - Certification of bill., 1785 October 31; 1 pg.; Duane, James, 1733-1797
    Concerns an affadavit. Bill is for legal costs in case between Charles Willing and John Carrew.
  - ALS to Richard Bache?, 1789 May 17-18; 4 pgs.; Bache, Sally
    News of home, events and deaths.
  - Bill of exchange, 1789 August 17; 1 pg.; Paxton, Cockerell & Co
    "Received of William Duane." Drawn on William Paxton & Co., London.
    Old call number B:D852.1. 1974 1471ms.
  - ALS to M? William Young, 1789 December 10; 2 pgs.; Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1755-1824
    Note requesting a copy of The Geography of the United States.
    Note comprises two pieces, signature separate. From scrapbook.
  - Memorandum of agreement:: Robert Jones, 1791 May 3; 1 pg.; Duane, William, 1760-1835
    OS
  - ALS to William Duane(1760-1835), 1791 May 18; 1 pg.; Richemont, J. B
    Letter of political support.
    Old call number B:D852.1. 1974 1471ms. OS
  - ALS to Samuel Myers, 1791 November 7; 2 pgs.; Girard, Stephen, 1750-1831
    Commercial matters involving the purchase of tobacco and coffee. Mentions the ship "Le Pere de Famille, " and merchants William and James Douglas.
    Old call number B:D852.1.
  - ALS to William Duane (1760-1835), 1793 February 17; 4 pgs.; Fenwick, C
    Concerns observations from the island? Of Pondechessy? made by Fenwick of the new French governor and delegation from the French National Assembly. Mentions cruel and capricious nature of the delegates and contemptable behavior of the new governor.
  - ALS to William Duane (1760-1835), 1793 April 13; 3 pgs.; Fenwick, C
    News from Europe.
  - ALS to the Treasurer of the Mint, 1794 November 14; 1 pg.; Rittenhouse, David, 1732-1796
  - ALS to William Duane (1760-1835), 1794 December 30; 2 pgs.; Shaw, E
  - AL to I. E. Hay, [1794]; 2 pgs.; Duane, William, 1760-1835
    Appeal to British government?
    Old call number B:D852.1. OS
  - Bill of sale to Edward Shaw, 1794; 4 pgs.; Duane, William, 1760-1835
    Sale of printing office in Calcutta to Edward Shaw.
  - Sale of property of William Duane (1760-1835), 1795 January 15; 6 pgs.; Unidentified
  - Testimony to court; Calcutta, India, 1795 August 26; 3 pgs.; Duane, William, 1760-1835
    Appeal to British authorities to reclaim lands seized by Sepoys in India.
  - Appeal to Governor of St. Helena, 1795; 4 pgs.; Duane, William, 1760-1835
    Objects to treatment at hands of British governor.
  - AL to governor of St. Helena, [1795]; 2 pgs.; Duane, William, 1760-1835
    Protests his being confined and prevention from going ashore on the island of St. Helena by the resident governor.
  - ALS to William Duane (1760-1835), 1800 December 2; 3 pgs.; Leib, Michael, 1761-1822
    Discusses national politics, especially the Jefferson vs. Burr presidential election. Mentions activities of individual states, and machinations in the U.S. House of Representatives.
  - ALS to Governor Brooks, ca 1800; 2 pgs.; Duane, William, 1760-1835
    Appeal to governor, rejects epitaph of "foreign incindiary."
  - Autograph, ca 1800; 1 pg.; McKean, Thomas, 1734-1817
  - Certificate of naturalization, 1802 July 14; 1 pg.; Duane, William, 1760-1835
    Old catalog number B:D852.1. Unlocated as of 11/28/07.
  - ALS to John Inskeep, 1805 March 2; 1 pg.; McKean, Thomas, 1734-1817
    Concerns acknowledgement of receipt of Inskeep's resignation as judge of the Court of Common Pleas for the county of Philadelphia. Accepts with regret.
  - ALS to unidentified, 1805 December 24; 1 pg.; Madison, James, 1751-1836
    Apology note.
  - ALS to James Greenleaf, 1806 January 18; 1 pg.; Duane, William John, 1780-1865
    Regards request for payment of bill on behalf of his father.
  - ALS to Frances Preston, 1806 August 10; 1 pg.; Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845
    Regards matter of debt owed by Jackson to Preston, regarding shipment of slaves, cotton and whiskey. Jackson claims he is trying to repay debt, "but mortals may strive, but cannot command the gods."
  - ALS to William Duane (1760-1835), 1807 May 24; 3 pgs.; Perdue, James
    Applies for a job as editor of the Aurora. Challenges Duane to a duel. Mentions trepidation on challenging him due to Duane's status as a Colonel.
    Old catalog number Misc. Ms. Coll. 1962 923ms.
  - ALS to Aaron Levy, 1808 February 1; 2 pgs.; Snyder, Simon, 1759-1819
    Regarding business matters with John Reichenbach and Jacob Hosterman. Discusses Mrs. Synder's illness and her use of cough drops.
  - Stock transfer, 1808 August 8; 1 pg.; Bartram, Moses
    Transfer to George W. Bartram of all shares...in the Library Company of Philadelphia.
  - ALS to Jonathan Smith, 1809 January 12; 1 pg.; Findlay, William, 1768-1846
    Encloses warrant. Thanks Smith for services in procurring exchange of damaged Trenton Bank notes and satin cloth.
  - ALS to William Duane (1760-1835), 1810 October 25; 1 pg.; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826
    Returns translated sheets. Will furnish a short epistle soon.
  - AQS, a fair copy, to Deborah Bache Duane, 1811 August 16; 2 pgs.; Duane, William John, 1780-1865
    Concerns resolution of Franklin's estate.
    Old catalog number Misc. Ms. Coll. 1974 712ms.
  - Indenture to Sarah Bache, 1812 January 14; 22 pgs.; Duane, William, 1760-1835
    Old catalog number Misc. Ms. Coll. 1959 537ph. Photocopy. Original Deed Book I p. 1-22. OS
    Concerning B.Franklin's estate. This was received from the Franklin Papers Office, Yale Univ.shipment, March 1959. Film 54-65 Frame 196.
  - Deed: beneficiary Louis Bache, 1812 May 9; 1 pg.; Sargent, Thomas
    Oversized vellum document.
  - ALS to Zebulon Pike, 1813 March 10; 3 pgs.; Duane, William, 1760-1835
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    Presented by Morris Duane; Dec. 1969.
    Informs Pike of mediated peace talks with Great Britain. Imparts plans for deployment of troops. Directs him in the deployment of platoons, and implores him to "depend on the bayonet."
    Old call number B:D852. 1970 128ms.
  - ALS to William John Duane, 1816 January 1; 2 pgs.; Sergeant, John, 1779-1852
    News of congressional activities. Discusses pending legal case. Mentions Mr. Binney and Mr. Walsh.
  - ALS to J. Robinson, 1816 January 27; 1 pg.; Duane, William John, 1780-1865
    Response to a circulation (Aurora) matter.
    Old call number B:D852.1. 1962 574ms.
  - Receipt to Abraham Yost, 1816 July 23; 1 pg.; Bank of the United States
  - Will, 1820 June 28; 7 pgs.; Bache, Catherine Wistar, 1770-1820
    Old call number B:D852.m.
    Refers to Richard Bache, Mrs. Sarah Bache, and Benjamin Franklin.
  - ALS to William John Duane, 1820 August 31; 3 pgs.; Conway, Frederick William
    Introduces a friend, Mr. Hamilton, who has been in South America. Reports the loss of three of his children in the last ten months. News of the divorce of king George IV. Predicts an "explosion" in Ireland.
  - Transfer of shares to William John? Duane, 1821 May 30; 1 pg.; Bartram, George Washington, 1784-1853
  - LS to William Duane (1760-1835), 1822 August 6; 1 pg.; Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848
    Requests that Duane forward an enlosed letter (missing) to a Mr. Ravenge.
  - ALS to William Duane (1760-1835), 1822 August 17; 2 pgs.; Clay, Henry, 1777-1852
    Reports death of Manuel Torres. Lists attributes of Torres, Columbia.
  - Jonathon [Thackara]: indenture, 1823 June 30; 1 pg.; Unidentified
    Remnant of indenture form.
  - ALS to Henry Simpson, 1823 December 8; 1 pg.; Roberts, Joseph, 1795-1849
    Roberts, as Cashier of Girard's bank, acknowledges a deposit.
  - ALS to William John Duane, 1825 February 12; 1 pg.; Clay, Henry, 1777-1852
    Response to letter on the 5th. Vaugue apology and pleasantries. Regarding Clay's acceptance of post as Secretary of State?
  - ALS to W. R. Idinor?, 1825 March 31; 1 pg.; Hopkinson, Joseph, 1770-1842
    Requests that package aboard Baltimore steam boat be delivered to Mr. Poinsett at Norfolk (VA) or held for later transport to Mexico.
  - ALS to William Duane (1808-1882), 1825 September 27; 4 pgs.; Duane, William John, 1780-1865
    Family news and advice. Admonishes son to keep practicing the flute, in preparation for a family concert. Mentions purchase of a piano, "the cost of which is considerable," books for his education, and a fur cap.
  - ALS to William Duane (1808-1882), 1825 October 23; 3 pgs.; Duane, Sarah, Catherine and Mary
    Discusses practice on various musical instruments, new purchases by father of furniture (stool), a new fireplace grate, family news and gossip.
    Old call number B:D852.2. 1977 32ms(1).
  - ALS to William Duane (1808-1882), 1825 November 3; 3 pgs.; Duane, William John, 1780-1865
    Advice on means to a happy life. Counsels son to be more interested in the future than family history.
  - ALS to William Duane (1808-1882), 1826 March 19; 3 pgs.; Duane, William John, 1780-1865
    Gives advice on education for a successful career. Mentions William Duane Jr.'s discontent with various schools, including West Point.
  - ALS to William Duane (1808-1882), 1826 April 7; 3 pgs.; Duane, William John, 1780-1865
    Personal advice on how to lead meaningful life.
  - ALS to William Duane (1808-1882), 1826 May 8; 4 pgs.; Duane, William John, 1780-1865
    Advice on choosing life's work. Mentions grandfather and grandmother (Richard and Sarah Franklin Bache).
  - ALS to William Duane (1808-1882), 1826 June 7; 1 pg.; Duane, William John, 1780-1865
    Acknowledges delivery of letter by a Mr. Bourse. Family news, especially of siblings.
  - ALS to Garret D. Wall, 1827 February 6; 1 pg.; Duane, William John, 1780-1865